Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. We're doing this remotely for me
as well. We pick up today's דף daf is ט"ז Taz-zayin 16.
We pick up four lines from the bottom
of ט"ו עמוד ב' Tes-vav amud bet where it
says ומנא תימא, u'minatema, excuse me, six lines from the bottom. So
the משנה mishna had said that you can שחט shacht with any
type of a knife, not even a knife, it could even be
a rock or reed as long as it was smooth enough. And
then it said however that you can also שחט shacht with as
I... oh, I'm sorry, it did say a rock and a reed,
which leads the גמרא Gemara into a conversation whether you can use
something that is attached to the ground.
So and we quoted a position of רבי Rebbi that said that
something that is attached to the ground is not valid. And the
משנה mishna actually also implies that לכתחילה lechatchila it's not valid. So
it's only valid בדיעבד, bedievid, post facto. So we said that both
our משנה mishna was רבי Rebbi as well, but that רבי Rebbi
post facto would allow a case where something started detached and was
attached later.
תלוש ולבסוף חיבור, talush u'levasof chibur, that that was not fully considered
attached as contrasted to something that was always attached מחובר מעיקרא. mechubar
me'ikara. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask how we
know to make a distinction between these two categories. So let's take
a look. Again, six lines from the bottom on ט"ו עמוד ב'.
Tes-vav amud bet. ומנא תימא דשאני לן בין מחובר מעיקרא לתלוש ולבסוף
חיבור. u'minatema d'shani lan bein mechubar me'ikara letalush u'levasof chibur. Where do
we know we make a distinction between something that is that was
always attached to something that was first detached and then attached? דתניא,
datanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, השוחט במוכני שחיטתו כשירה. hashochet
b'muchni shechitasto keshera.
If you שחט shacht with a wheel, some type of a knife
that is being moved through a water wheel or some other type
of a wheel power, then it's valid. We'll look at that in
a moment. The use of some type of a mechanism.
במחובר לקרקע שחיטתו כשירה, bimechubar lekarka shechitasto keshera, if it's something that
is if the knife is attached to the ground, it's valid. And
then it goes on to say נתץ סכין בכותל ושחט בה שחיטתו
כשירה. natatz sakin bakotel v'shachat ba shechitasto keshera. Another example of something
attached which started its life as detached. If you took a knife
and you stuck it into a wall, it was a good שחיטה.
shechita. Now by the way, it's important to note, how are you
able to do a שחיטה shechita here if these things are attached
to the ground? How do you move them? So if you take
a look at רש"י, Rashi, the small little רש"י Rashi at the
bottom makes a very critical point. נתץ סכין בכותל, natatz sakin bakotel,
says רש"י, Rashi, והוליך והביא צואר הבהמה עליה. v'holich v'heivi tzavar habeheima
aleha. You do not actually move the knife. What you did was
you moved the neck of the animal. So this is obviously a
big surprise for us. We always assumed that you have to move
the knife, but actually it's not true. As long as you have
the right type of a סכין sakin and it is cutting the
animal through a cutting motion, even if that motion is being done
to the animal and not to the knife, all movement is relative
apparently, then that is valid. Okay, so the first thing the משנה
mishna says is if it's attached to a water wheel or it's
some type of a wheel or it's stuck in a wall, it's
a valid שחיטה shechita מחובר לקרקע. mechubar lekarka. Then the משנה mishna
goes on and says the following, excuse me, the ברייתא braita goes
on and says the following. הצור יוצא מן הכותל, hatzoer yotzei min
hakotel, let's say you had a rock protruding from a wall, או
קנה עולה מאליו, o kane olei me'eilav, or you had a reed
growing from the swamp, but it was not it had been it
was growing actually. ושחט בו שחיטתו פסולה, v'shachat bo shechitasto pesula,
it's invalid. So what's the difference? In one case we say attached
is good and in the other case we say attached is no
good. So the גמרא Gemara continues, קשיא אהדדי, kashya ahadadei,
this is mutually these two things contradict one another. אלא לאו שמע
מינה שאני בין מחובר מעיקרא לתלוש ולבסוף חיבור. ela lav shema mina
shani bein mechubar me'ikara letalush u'levasof chibur.
There's a difference between something that was always attached to something that
was detached and later attached. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a
good proof. Now, meaning that the case of היה מחובר לקרקע haya
mechubar lekarka in the ברייתא braita meant something that you attached to
the ground.
Where that בדיעבד bedievid is good. Whereas the case of a reed
growing or a rock, that's something that was always attached and that
is no good. Now the problem is is that it says צור
יוצא מן הכותל, tzoer yotzei min hakotel, a rock coming out of
a wall. A wall presumably is man-made and was built. But the
גמרא Gemara will later say that no, we're talking here about a
natural wall, a wall for example of a cave. So that type
of a rock coming out of a natural wall, that is always
attached and that is no good. So here's a very important
distinction which the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on for most
of today's דף daf between how do you define what does it
mean to be attached. Does attached mean that it was always attached
or does attached mean that it is currently attached to the ground
תלוש ולבסוף חיבור. talush u'levasof chibur. And the גמרא Gemara here is
saying that actually if it was man it was attached by human
agency תלוש ולבסוף חיבור, talush u'levasof chibur, that is not really considered
attached and according to רבי, Rebbi, at least even who says it's
invalid it's פסול pasul when it was always attached in this type
of a case בדיעבד bedievid at least it will be valid. Presumably
לכתחילה lechatchila not because you can come to mix up the two
cases, but at least post facto this is not really considered attached.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn its attention to
exactly this issue and the definition of what does it mean to
be מחובר mechubar and what does it mean to be לא מחובר.
lo mechubar. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this.
אמר מר. Amar Mar. So we taught. השוחט במוכני. Ha-shocheit be-mukhni.
I'm sorry, before we get to מחובר mechubar we're first going to
explore for a minute this issue of being attached to the wheel.
So the ברייתא baraita says that somebody who slaughters with a knife
that is attached to a wheel, שחיטתו כשרה, shechitatu kesheira, it's valid.
והתניא שחיטתו פסולה. Ve-ha-tanya shechitatu pesula.
We have a similar ברייתא baraita that says that exactly in this
case if it's somehow being propelled through the mechanism of a wheel,
it's invalid. By the way, you know, it does not mean just
because it's attached to the wheel that the knife is moving in
a circle. Obviously, you can't שחט shecht if the knife is moving
in a circle. But if anybody ever knows about any basic mechanism,
you take the energy of a wheel and you can transform it
into a vertical motion. So you're using the energy of the turning
of a wheel to create a machine which moves the knife vertically.
So our ברייתא baraita said that that's good, but we have another
ברייתא baraita that said it's invalid. So the גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בסדנא דפחרא הא בסדנא דמיא.
Ha be-sadna de-pakhra, ha be-sadna de-maya.
Is it a wheel used for pottery or is it a water
wheel? Obviously, the modifier here is different. Pottery is not the means
of its movement, it's what it's being used for. It's a wheel
that you spin with like your leg motion, with a pedal motion
to spin a wheel to make pottery. I think we're all familiar
with that. And a water wheel is something that spins on the
basis of the movement of the water. So how are these two
different? They're different in an obvious way. If you have a pottery
wheel, the energy is coming through you, through your leg pushing the
pedal, spinning the wheel and so on. So ultimately, although you're using
a mechanism, the mechanism is being driven by human energy. Whereas in
the case of the water wheel, the energy is coming through the
rushing water. So this gives us another criteria for שחיטה. shechita. We
talked about the fact that the שחיטה shechita can be with any
type of a knife, as long as it's sharp enough, it doesn't
even have to be recognized as a vessel. We also talked about
an earlier discussion that שחיטה shechita might not require any intention. But
one of the things that שחיטה shechita does require is what is
here not being exactly articulated, the concept, but it's implicit, and that's
a concept called כח גברא, koach gavra, the energy of a person,
human energy. So although you do not have to have intention for
the act, the energy for the act has to come from a
person. So if you, for example, had a knife that was on
a table and a wind blew it off
and somehow magically this שחטed shecht an animal, that would not be
a שחיטה. shechita. מעשה שחיטה Ma'aseh shechita requires human energy even if
it might not require intention. כח גברא. koach gavra. So a water
wheel does not have כח גברא, koach gavra, whereas a pottery wheel
does. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue to analyze
this. So let's take a look. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it eima, if you
want you could say, הא והא בסדנא דמיא. ha ve-ha be-sadna de-maya.
No, actually, both can be cases of a water wheel. There's a
case where a water wheel is no good, there's a case where
a water wheel is good. What's the difference? ולא
קשיא, Ve-lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בכח ראשון הא בכח שני.
Ha be-koach rishon ha be-koach sheini. Is it your first power or
your second power?
What does that mean? It means how did the water wheel get
started? Let's take a look. So presumably you've got a river that
runs by and you've got some type of a sluice gate or
whatever it is that you could open up and divert the river,
and the water of the river will come into your channel and
it will spin the water wheel. So who opens up those sluice
gates to get the water of the river to go into your
wheel? So that would be the question about you ultimately are playing
a role. You're obviously not imparting the energy of the rushing water,
that's coming from the water itself, but you somehow are bringing that
water to your wheel. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara compares
it. הא בכח ראשון הא בכח שני, Ha be-koach rishon ha be-koach
sheini, כי הא דאמר רב פפא, ki ha de-amar Rav Pappa, like
רב פפא Rav Pappa says, האי מאן דכפתיה לחבריה ואשקליה בדקא דמיא
ומית חייב. hai man de-kaftay le-khavray ve-ashkeilay bidka de-maya u-mit chayav. So
somebody came and he bound his friend, he took his friend, not
such a friend, and he tied him up, and what did he
do? He put him right in front of these sluice gates right
by a rushing river. And then you opened up the sluice gates
and the water came crashing down and the guy died. So the
person is חייב, chayav, he killed him by opening up the sluice
gate. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? גירי דידיה נינהו. Giray
didei ninhu. They're his arrows. Which means that although it's not his
energy that's in the water, but since the water came and burst
through because of his act of opening up the gates, it's considered
like he shot the water, like he shot an arrow, even though
again the water had energy without him.
But the statement goes on, גירי דידיה דהני בי giray didei de-hani
bei that helped him, meaning that was impacted, that made, that created
this water, that led this water to crash into this guy. והני
מילי, v'hanei milei, but that's only true בכוח ראשון, bekoach rishon, if
it's your first energy. אבל בכוח שני, aval bekoach sheni, if it
is the second power, גרמא בעלמא הוא, grama b'alma hu, it is
only indirect causation. Now, what does second power mean? The way רש״י
Rashi explains it, it means that imagine this person is not right
in front of the sluice gates at the bottom of this dam;
he is actually a little bit removed. So when the sluice gates
are opened, the water comes crashing down and it hits the area
directly below it. Person isn't there in the area directly below it.
After the water hits that area of the floor directly below it,
it then continues to move on and then it drowns the person
who is standing a few feet back. So there what we say
is, when I removed the sluice gates, the crashing down of the
water, that was like I had shot that arrow. I had made
that water crash down. I had thrown that water. That hit the
base, and that hit the base. If he was at the base,
I would have thrown the water on him effectively and killed him.
But he wasn't at the base; he was ten feet away. So
I threw the water down at the base, and then the water
moved and it killed him afterwards. That was not my energy; that
was a derivative of my energy, and therefore I am not חייב.
chayav. So this is a pretty amazing idea. Obviously I caused his
death, but in הלכה, halacha, both for murder and even for issues
of נזק nezek damages, it's not about causation, it's about the action
itself. And since this is not my energy but something that derived
from it, a כוח שני, koach sheni, I am going to be
exempt. So this becomes a very interesting and important halachic concept for
many areas about defining what is considered to be my act and
not my act in a way, although it's obviously troubling to say
that I would be exempt although the guy dies just because he's
a few feet away, and that's a separate discussion. And the רמב״ם
Rambam makes a special point, the גמרא Gemara makes a special point
about חייב בדיני שמיים, chayav b'dinei shamayim, that I'm obviously liable as
far as heaven is concerned and maybe the court would have a
way of dealing with me if not through a formal process. But
what is more sort of interesting for us is that even when
it is demanded that I do an action, I don't have to
be providing the energy itself; if I release energy, then the initial
impact is considered to be mine as well. So here too, if
I have a water wheel and I release the energy of the
water, I open up the gate that allows the river to rush
through, that initial turning of the wheel that comes through the energy
I immediately release, that would actually be considered my action. As the
river continues to push the wheel, then it's just happening on its
own, it's no longer my energy, but that original push is considered
to be כוח ראשון koach rishon and is considered to be my
energy. So this is
relevant for a number of issues. For example,
describing the difference between action and גרמא. grama. So for example, let's
talk about turning on the lights on שבת. Shabbat. So let's assume
for argument's sake that an incandescent light is אש. esh. It heats
up a piece of metal, it causes it to glow; that, let's
assume that that is generally assumed that that is אש. esh. Now,
do I actually heat up that piece of metal? Well, if you
look at what I do at a micro level, what I actually
do is I close a circuit by switching the light, and because
I close a circuit, that then leads to the electrons moving and
ultimately going into that piece of metal and heating it up and
causing the light to go on. Of course this happens so instantaneously
that we're not aware of the time lapse, but effectively I did
not heat that piece of metal; I closed a circuit and then,
if you would, the water, the electrons rushed through this closed circuit
and heated up that piece of metal. So in general, this we
consider this to not be גרמא, grama, we consider this to be
מעשה ma'aseh
for exactly the reason here of the sluice gates. I did it,
it happened immediately, so the immediacy is relevant, and because it happened
immediately, it is considered like I actually did the thing itself, like
I turned on the light itself. So here's an interesting example לחומרא
l'chumra where it's important to say that גרמא, grama, although it can
be broken down into stages and it's not my energy, when it's
an immediate result and I'm like releasing some power, it's considered like
I did it. Interesting other cases to ask about in general are
about things that you turn on with electricity and then they continue
on their own, like the whole issue about machine-made מצה matzah and
is it being made לשמה? lishma? And is the fact that I
turned on the machine, does that mean what happens afterwards is all
considered to be mine? Here at least it seems very clearly there
you don't need כוח גברא, koach gavra, you more need כוונה, kavana,
but here it seems very clearly that at least what happens afterwards,
after the initial spurt, that is not considered my direct action, that's
considered my
גרמא. grama. another criteria by שחיטה, shechita, which is called כוח גברא,
koach gavra, human energy, to make it a human action, maybe not
intention, but human energy, and that that is either the actual physical
imparting of energy, the use of the waterwheel, excuse me, of the
pottery wheel, the pushing of the wheel, or that if I release
the energy, that initial spurt is considered mine, and that's the case
of the waterwheel and the initial turning. Okay, now we go back
to our major theme, which is that of מחובר לקרקע. mechubar l'karka.
So let's take a look.
יתיב רב
אחורי דרבי חייא. yativ Rav achorei d'Rabbi Chiyya. So רב Rav was
sitting behind רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiyya. Remember רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya is
the one that says מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka is not a problem
by שחיטה shechita if the knife is attached to the ground. ורבי
חייא קמי דרבי, v'Rabbi Chiyya kammai d'Rabbi, and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
was sitting in front of רבי, Rebbe, and רבי Rebbe is the
one that says that the knife cannot be attached to the ground.
So here, by the way, you have three very important generations of
transitioning from תנאים tannaim to אמוראים: amoraim: רבי, Rebbe, the author of
the המשנה, Hamishnah, the editor of the המשנה, Hamishnah, רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiyya, who sort of edited the תוספתא Tosefta and the ברייתא, braita,
and then רב, Rav, who was the first of the אמוראים. amoraim.
Anyway, so they were sitting here in front of רבי, Rebbe, רב
Rav behind רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya in front
of
רבי. Rebbe. ויתיב רבי וקאמר מנין לשחיטה שהוא בתלוש? v'yativ Rebbe v'ka'amar
minayin l'shechita shehu betalush? How do you know that שחיטה shechita requires
that the knife be not attached to the ground, be disconnected? שנאמר,
she'ne'emar, as the verse says, ויקח את המאכלת לשחוט את בנו. vayikach
et hama'achelet lishchot et b'no. They took off את בנו. et b'no.
So this obviously is a verse that was quoted in the גמרא
Gemara in זבחים Zevachim as well, to learn laws of שחיטה shechita
by קדשים. kodashim. Always very troubling, the deriving of these laws from
the attempted offering and slaughtering of יצחק. Yitzchak. And here it says
that he took the knife to slaughter, so מאכלת לשחוט. ma'achelet lishchot.
So we're saying it's a knife to slaughter, so it has to
be something that is a vessel, that's a knife that's detached. Now,
by the way, רבי Rebbe never says it requires to be a
vessel, a rock that is detached or a reed that is detached
has no הלכה halacha status as a vessel. For קדשים, kodashim, we
learn from this verse that you need to be a vessel, maybe
even a כלי שרת, kli sharet, but something at least that is
recognized as a vessel. By שחיטה, shechita, by normal שחיטה, shechita, we're
not learning that, and at most what we're learning is that according
to רבי, Rebbe, it needs to be detached. So that's where he
learned it from, from the word מאכלת. ma'achelet. אמר ליה רב לרבי
חייא מאי קאמר? amar lei Rav l'Rabbi Chiyya mai ka'amar? So רב
Rav said to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, what's he saying? So רש״י
Rashi has two versions, but it's possible what he's basically saying is
he was sitting so far back, he didn't hear. He said, hey,
what did רבי Rebbe say? I heard him quote a פסוק, pasuk,
but what's he using that פסוק pasuk for? So what's he saying?
So the answer was, so
אמר ליה, amar lei, so מאי קאמר, mai ka'amar, what's רבי Rebbe
saying? So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya said
to רב: Rav: ו דכתיב אאופצא קאמר. vav deketiv a'uptza ka'amar. He's
saying a ו vav written on a ridge. What the heck does
this mean? This is an idiomatic expression, but you imagine a bumpy
type of a ridge and you try to write a ו vav
on it, a line on it, the line is going to be
chopped up, it's going to be broken up into parts. You can't
make a straight line because obviously you're running over all of these
bumps. So it's a way of saying he's saying something that's not
such a good idea. He's trying to draw a straight line on
a ridge and it's all broken up. So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
said, yeah, he's trying to use this פסוק pasuk to argue that
you need a vessel for שחיטה, shechita, but of course, you can't
really bring any proof from this verse. Now, we would say you
can't bring a verse, proof from the verse, because first of all,
that's just what happened, he used a knife. And second of all,
who says that you learn from this general laws of שחיטה? shechita?
But let's see why the גמרא Gemara says you can't use the
verse. So the גמרא Gemara says: והא קרא קאמר. ve'ha kra ka'amar.
One minute, he's using a פסוק. pasuk. What's wrong with the פסוק?
pasuk? The פסוק pasuk says מאכלת לשחוט, ma'achelet lishchot, you need something
like a knife to do שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara says:
לא קרא לזריזותיה דאברהם קמשמע לן, lo kra l'zrizutei d'Avraham kamma'shma lan,
which is more or less saying the Torah's just a narrative, it's
telling you that how,
the alacrity of אברהם, Avraham, that he was
so rushing to do the מצוה, mitzvah, and therefore he took a
knife. And the way רש״י Rashi explains it is he wants to
make sure maybe there wouldn't have been a knife up where he
was actually going to do the עקידה. akeidah. And that seems to
have been perhaps the proof. Why did אברהם Avraham have to take
a knife? Why didn't he just find a rock that was there
and sharpen it? So you see that you can't use something attached.
Of course, that's not a proof because if he could have used
a rock, he could have also pulled the rock out of the
ground. But anyway, אברהם Avraham was taking a knife, it was telling
you that he was preparing to do the שחיטה, shechita, and you
cannot learn from this any principle of what is and is not
a valid thing to do a שחיטה shechita with. Okay, so now
we've learned that you need שחיטה shechita to be כוח גברא, koach
gavra, human energy, an interesting discussion of how do you define that
energy. And we've also learned that what we've been saying, that there's
a debate of רבי Rebbe and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya whether שחיטה
shechita requires that the knife be, or whatever you're using, be attached
or be detached, and רבי Rebbe says it has to be detached.
And now we're going to go back to look at how do
you define, what does it mean to be attached, what does it
mean to be detached? Let's take a look. אמר רב. amar Rav.
So Rava says, פשיטא לי, Peshita li, it's obvious to me, תלוש
שבסוף חיברו לענין עבודת כוכבים הוי תלוש. talush she'basof chibro l'inyan avodat
kochavim havei talush. So Rava says, פשיטא לי, Peshita li, it's obvious
to me, תלוש שבסוף חיברו לענין עבודת כוכבים הוי תלוש. talush she'basof
chibro l'inyan avodat kochavim havei talush. Something that was once detached and
now has been attached to the ground, for purposes of עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, of idol worship, it's considered detached. What's the principle, why
do I care if it's attached or detached?
Because, well let's take a look, because we have taught, המשתחוה לבית
שלו אסרו. ha'mishtachaveh l'bayit shelo assaro. If a person bows down to
his own house, then the house is forbidden in benefit. Now the
key principle, the key here is שלו, shelo, his own house, because
the הלכה halacha is אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam
oser davar she'eino shelo. You cannot make something that belongs to your
friend, to somebody else, forbidden through your actions as long as you
have not physically changed the object. If you שחט shacht your friend's
cow for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it does become an offering to
עבודה זרה avoda zara and forbidden in benefit. But if you just
bow down to your friend's house, so you have not done a
physical action that changed it, so therefore you cannot change the status
of something that belongs to somebody else. You can change the status
of something that belongs to you. So therefore, if you bow down
to your own house, you make it forbidden. However, there's one other
criteria. You can only make something an object of worship to become
forbidden if it is considered detached. If it is considered attached to
the ground, you cannot do this. So here you worship, you bow
down to your house. Well, if you made your house forbidden, it
shows we consider the house to not be מחובר לקרקע, mechubar l'karka,
to not be considered attached. Let's continue and see where the גמרא
Gemara says this. ואי סלקא דעתך הוי מחובר, v'ei salka da'atach havei
mechubar, if you think that we consider that something that was once
detached and is now attached is considered attached, so that you wouldn't
make it forbidden because we have a principle. The principle says אלהיהם
על ההרים, eloheihem al he'harim, based on the verse in דברים, Devarim,
it says their gods that are on the mountains, and from which
we say the gods are on the mountains, ולא ההרים אלהיהם, v'lo
he'harim eloheihem, but the mountains themselves can never be considered their gods.
So actually this is stated in a very strong statement in the
גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, that if somebody bows down
to a mountain as to worship it, this person has done an
act of עבודה זרה avoda zara and is חייב מיתה, chayav mita,
punishable by death. So obviously a person can do an act of
עבודה זרה avoda zara to a mountain, you can do an act
of עבודה זרה avoda zara to an unseen god, but the mountain
itself does not become defined as an object of עבודה זרה avoda
zara and does not become forbidden in benefit. A good thing because
if so, then there would be major parts of the globe that
would actually be of the earth itself that would be considered עבודה
זרה avoda zara and forbidden in benefit. So that is not true.
It can only be something that is detached, which makes sense because
it has to be considered sort of under human control to be
able to designate its identity. So if it's part of the earth,
you cannot really designate its identity, I should have said identity, unless
it is actually מטלטלין, metaltelin, detached. Okay, so now we have said,
so what do we see by עבודה זרה? avoda zara? You cannot
make something that's attached to the ground considered עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
but you can make a house considered עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So
you see that if it started its life as detached, even if
it's not a full house detached but it was, you know, bricks
and wood and whatever it was, and you then attached it to
the ground, so then it is considered for עבודה זרה avoda zara
purposes to be detached and can actually become forbidden as עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. So that's in terms of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, we
consider it to be not attached. Now we're going to look at
other areas of הלכה halacha where we're going to assume that the
status is not necessarily the same in other areas of הלכה. halacha.
So let's take a look. ולענין הכשר זרעים, u'l'inyan hechsher zera'im, when
it comes to making seeds forbidden, excuse me, seeds meaning
agricultural products susceptible to become טמא, tamei, which happens when they come
in contact with water, תנאי היא, tanna'ei hi, it's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. Now, before we see it, I'll just say look, we
obviously know that what we know that water when it comes in
contact with food makes the food susceptible to become טמא. tamei. However,
we obviously know that that's only relevant after the food has been
cut, because if it were true when the food was growing, then
the הלכה halacha would be meaningless because all hopefully all agricultural products
have come in contact with water during their growing process. So it's
only when they're no longer attached to the ground. Now, that is
true both of the food, but it's also interestingly true in general
in terms of whatever the water becomes comes in contact with, because
if you might remember from a day or two ago, if the
water touches the fruit but you're not interested in the water, you
don't want the fruit to become טמא, tamei, then the fruit does
not become הוכשר, huchshar, does not become susceptible. Let's say you're interested
in the water but not for the sake of the fruit. Let's
say you put out your car and you were too lazy to
get a car wash and you were hoping it was going to
rain so that your car would get wet, and the water hit
the car. Okay? And then you left a piece on that water.
So that type of a case, the piece would become susceptible, הוכשר,
huchshar, even if you didn't want the piece wet because you wanted
the water and you wanted the water for the sake of. something
that was not attached to the ground. So the same way if
you want the water to go on the peach and it's not
attached to the ground, it makes it susceptible, if you want the
water to go on the car, which isn't attached, that then means
that the water now can make the peach susceptible even if you
didn't want the water on the peach. So the basic point is,
you want the water for the sake of something that is not
attached to the ground. What if the thing you want the water
for was detached and is now attached? תלוש ולבסוף חיברו. talush u-levasof
chibro. Will that make the water able to make the fruit susceptible?
That's our question. So let's take a look. דתנן. de-tenan. So לעניין
הכשר זרעים, le-inyan hechshre zerayim, when it comes to issues of making
seeds food susceptible, so תנאי היא, tannai hi, it's a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. דתנן, de-tenan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. הכופה קערה
על הכותל בשביל שתודח. ha-kofeh kearah al ha-kotel bishvil she-tudach. So instead
of a car, use the example here of a vessel, you put
a vessel on a wall because you were expecting rain and you
wanted the vessel to get cleaned out by the rain. הרי זה
בכי יותן. harei zeh be-chi yutan. So the verse is כי יותן
ki yutan when מים mayim hits a fruit, so meaning, and that
means that you desire the water, so in this case, since you
desired the water for the vessel, this water can now make stuff
susceptible for טומאה. tumah. בשביל שלא ילקה הכותל, bishvil shelo yilkeh ha-kotel,
let's say you put the vessel on the wall because you were
protecting the wall. So you didn't want the vessel to become wet.
You just wanted to protect the wall. אינו בכי יותן. eino be-chi
yutan. Then it is then you don't want the water and the
water will not make food susceptible. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
this is once again a problem of the excluded middle. You have
one extreme where you wanted the water, the other extreme where you
didn't want the water on the vessel or on the wall. What
about a middle case where you wanted the water on the wall?
So let's take a look. הגופא קשיא, ha gufa kashya, there's an
implicit internal contradiction. אמרת בשביל שתודח הרי זה בכי יותן. amarta bishvil
she-tudach harei zeh be-chi yutan. If you want the vessel cleaned out,
then the water is in the category of כי יותן ki yutan
when מים mayim is put, when water is put, meaning that the
water can make things susceptible. הא בשביל שיודח הכותל. ha bishvil she-yudach
ha-kotel.
So if you just wanted the water not for the vessel, but
you wanted the water for the wall, then the implication is אינו
בכי יותן. eino be-chi yutan. It's not, doesn't make things susceptible. והדר
תני, ve-hadar tanei, and then the end of the ברייתא Baraita went
to the opposite extreme of the משנה. Mishnah. בשביל שלא ילקה הכותל
אינו בכי יותן. bishvil shelo yilkeh ha-kotel eino be-chi yutan.
If you're trying to protect the wall, you don't want the water
at all, then the water does not make anything susceptible. הא בשביל
שיודח הכותל, ha bishvil she-yudach ha-kotel, if you wanted the water but
you wanted it not for a vessel, you wanted it for a
wall, הרי זה בכי יותן. harei zeh be-chi yutan. Then the water
does make things susceptible. Excuse me one second. Okay. I'm back. Yeah.
I'm back. Okay.
הרי זה בכי יותן. harei zeh be-chi yutan.
So then the water does make things susceptible if you did want
it, even if you only wanted it for the wall. Now obviously
the issue here with the wall, in the way it's different from
the vessel, is that it's something that was once detached but is
now attached. So what is the story with the middle case when
you want the water for the wall and not for the vessel?
So אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, so רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
said, תברה, tavrah, break the משנה Mishnah up. מי ששנה זו לא
שנה זו. mi she-shanah zu lo shanah zu. You're right. The who
taught the first half of the משנה Mishnah did not teach the
second half of the משנה. Mishnah. The middle case which is not
being discussed, which the implications are different, that's really a debate between
the first half and the second half of the משנה. Mishnah. So
there basically is a debate of the תנאים, tannaim, the anonymous תנאים,
tannaim, what is the story when you want the water for the
wall. That's what he says. And that's the opinion that it's a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, רב פפא
Rav Pappa says כולה חד תנא הוא. kulei chad tanna hu. No,
it's all one תנא. tanna. הא בכותל מערה הא בכותל בניין. ha
be-kotel mearah ha be-kotel binyan. Remember what type of a wall are
we talking about? Not all walls were built. Are we talking about
the wall of a cave? Are we talking about a constructed wall?
So he says we're talking about implicitly two different types of walls.
This is again as I said earlier we're talking about the wall
of a cave. So let's take a look. והכי קאמר, ve-hachi ka-amar,
here's how you read it. הכופה קערה על הכותל ha-kofeh kearah al
ha-kotel בשביל שתודח. bishvil she-tudach. If you put the vessel on the
wall because you wanted the vessel cleaned out, הרי זה בכי יותן.
harei zeh be-chi yutan. Then the water is susceptible. הא בשביל שיודח
הכותל, ha bishvil she-yudach ha-kotel, if you only wanted the wall to
be washed, אינו בכי יותן, eino be-chi yutan, the water does not
make things susceptible because it's considered attached. במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim
amurim, when is this true? בכותל מערה, be-kotel mearah, if it is
the wall of a cave. Therefore you want the water for something
attached to the ground. אבל בכותל בניין, aval be-kotel binyan, but if
it is a constructed wall, בשביל שלא ילקה הכותל הוא דאינו בכי
יותן. bishvil shelo yilkeh ha-kotel hu de-eino be-chi yutan. Then the only
way the water will not make things susceptible is if you're trying
to keep the water away, to protect the wall. הא בשביל שיודח
הכותל, ha bishvil she-yudach ha-kotel, but if you want the wall to
be washed and it is a constructed wall, הרי זה בכי יותן.
harei zeh be-chi yutan. Then it is in the category of כי
יותן. ki yutan. Then it does make, then it does make fruit
susceptible. So what have we said now? We have said that when
it comes to שחיטה, shechitah, although we have yet to revisit that,
when something is detached and later attached, it's considered to be not
attached. We said by עבודה זרה avodah zarah when it was תלוש
ולבסוף חיברו talush u-levasof chibro it's considered not attached. And we have
now said that by
הכשר זרעים. hechshre zerayim. as well as the other two, is also
considered to be detached, not attached. So we have a consistent position
of תלוש ולסוף חיברו talush ul'sof chibro is not considered to be
attached. What is interesting is that there was a possibility raised that
it might depend on the different area of הלכה. halacha. For עבודה
זרה avodah zarah maybe it's considered to be detached and for הכשר
זרעים hechsher zeroyim maybe it's a debate of תנאים. tenaim. So why
should it be different for different area of הלכה? halacha? Let's think
about that. We'll get back to that. Let's see first where the
גמרא gemara goes with this as it continues. So בעי רבא. ba'ei
Rava. So רבא Rava asked,
whoops, am I at the end here? Yeah. Next page.
Okay.
תלוש ולסוף חיברו לעניין שחיטה מאי? talush ul'sof chibro l'inyan shechita mai?
So now at the top of טז עמוד ב. Tet-Zayin amud Bet.
So although before we said that detached and later attached is considered
to be תלוש, talush, detached, now that we're revisiting it, we're asking
this question again. What is the story about תלוש ולסוף חיברו? talush
ul'sof chibro? So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. היה צור
יוצא מן הכותל, haya tzur yotzei min hakotel, the ברייתא beraita we
quoted before, if there was a rock coming out of a wall,
או שהיה קנה עולה מאליו, o shehaya kaneh oleh me'elav, or a
reed growing on itself, ושחט בו, v'shachat bo, and you slaughtered with
it, שחיטתו פסולה, shechitatu pesula, it's invalid. So there it sounds like
a wall is a constructed wall and it's considered still to be
attached. So the גמרא gemara says, sorry, and you see it's invalid.
So הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, no, maybe we're not talking
about something constructed and attached later. What are we talking about? בכותל
מערה, b'chotel me'arah, about a wall of a cave, something that was
always attached. דיקא נמי דקתני דומיא דקנה עולה מאליו, deika nami d'katani
dumya d'kaneh oleh me'elav, the inference is there because it sounds from
the text it's made a comparison to the reed. So the same
way a reed was something that was never attached later but naturally
grew, presumably it's the same type of a case with the rock
in the wall. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good inference.
So we still have an open question about how to treat this
for שחיטה. shechita. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. נעץ סכין
בכותל ושחט, na'atz sakkin b'kotel v'shachat, שחיטתו כשירה. shechitatu kesheira. So the
other ברייתא beraita said that if somebody took a knife and inserted
it into a wall, it's a good שחיטה. shechita. So there you
have it, that's our case about detached and now attached, and we
see that it is considered to be detached, תלוש. talush. So that's
a pretty good case. So no, the גמרא gemara says, שאני סכין
דלא מבטליה. shani sakkin d'lo mevatlei. No, that's not relevant at all.
There you never really fully attaching the knife to the wall to
the ground, you're not going to leave it like that, you plan
on eventually taking the knife back out. So it never becomes considered
to be, you know, as one, something that is now attached to
the ground. So therefore that's not a good case. We're looking for
something that started its life detached and now is really considered to
be, you know, connected to the ground. Like you build a house,
you build a wall. Something like this always retains its identity as
a knife. Okay. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. במחובר לקרקע,
b'mchubar l'karka, it says if you stuck your knife in a wall
or anything attached to the ground, שחיטתו כשירה, shechitatu kesheira, it's valid.
So it sounds like anything similar to the knife, even if you
build a wall, build a house, anything that began as תלוש talush
would be valid. אמר amar says no, דילמא סיפא כמפרשא לה, dilma
seifa k'mefarsha lah, maybe it is explicating what it had said, meaning
the knife example was said last. The מחובר לקרקע mchubar l'karka is
more abstract case was said second in the ברייתא. beraita. מאי מחובר
לקרקע? mai mchubar l'karka? What do we mean when we say something
attached to the ground is okay? סכין דלא מבטליה, sakkin d'lo mevatlei,
only a case like a knife which you are not annulling,
that you are not leaving there, that's a type of מחובר mchubar
which is considered to be תלוש. talush. But something that you really
plan on leaving and leaving attached, that might be considered to be
מחובר. mchubar. One minute let me just check this ברייתא beraita second.
Right,
okay, sakkin. All right, so that so we cannot prove it from
there. All
right, so now we're going to go on and we leave it
as an open question as opposed to before where we said that
according to רבי Rebbi it definitely would be valid, here we're saying
that we're not really certain what רבי Rebbi would say about this
case. So I want to for a moment reflect on the issue
that it's possible that different הלכות halachot treat the category of תלוש
ולסוף חיברו talush ul'sof chibro differently. I should also by the way
point out that there is an important question about טומאה tumah about
how we treat something about תלוש ולסוף חיברו. talush ul'sof chibro. You
know, can something that is attached to the ground now become טמא?
tamei? Can a house become טמא? tamei? Can, you know, various things
that are attached to the house become טמא? tamei? How do you
treat those areas? So there's a lot of different areas of הלכה
halacha where this question about תלוש ולסוף חיברו talush ul'sof chibro matters.
I would suggest, you know, the difference here is about what concept
we're trying to satisfy. Are we, you know, you could just say
it's a gray area so sometimes we rule one way, sometimes the
other, but I would like to be a little bit more precise
and say that it's a question about how we are conceptualizing it.
Are we trying to define something as attached or are we trying
to define something as the actual ground itself, the earth itself? For
example, the case of עבודה זרה avodah zarah which was the most
obvious, the principle was אלהיהם על ההרים ולא ההרים אלהיהם. eloheihem al
heharim v'lo heharim eloheihem. The mountains don't become gods. So there the
principle was you can't turn the earth Part of our very
of the very land itself, you cannot turn the land into an
idol. So there the issue was that something has to be considered
the earth, it has to be considered the ground. If you have
something like you built a house, it's attached to the ground, it's
מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, but it's not קרקע. karka. So there maybe
the principle is that it has to be considered קרקע karka not
מחובר לקרקע. mechubar lekarka. Whereas in other
areas, what we're really interested in, what we're saying is we're not
excluding it because it's ground, what we're really demanding is that you
use something that is considered to be vessel-like. So for example, the
שחיטה shechitah possibility, I would argue the concept is not that it
has to be considered קרקע karka to be invalid ground, but more
according to רבי, Rebbi, the idea it has to be like a
מאכלת, ma'achelet, like a knife. It has to be something that is
מטלטלין, metaltelin, that is movables. Something that is attached to the ground
in a permanent way is not considered a movable. So what I'm
saying really is that the middle case is again the issue of
excluded middle, because you can describe things at both extremes. You can
say there's one category called קרקע, karka, ground. There's another category called
מטלטלין, metaltelin, chattel. What about the middle category called מחובר לקרקע? mechubar
lekarka? It's attached to the ground, so it's not chattel, but on
the other hand, it's not actual ground itself, because it's only attached
to the ground. So some הלכות halachot like the עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, the emphasis is if it's the ground it's valid, it's not
an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Other הלכות halachot might not be about
the ground, might be about it being chattel, movables, and if it's
currently attached it is not considered to be a movable. That's how
I would explain the possibility that this הלכה halachah differs from area
to area. I should also say that obviously when it comes to
issues of let's say transactions and purchasing, the הלכה halachah clearly is
that things that are מחובר לקרקע mechubar lekarka like a house, you
buy and sell it not through things like משיכה meshichah because you
can't even do משיכה meshichah on a house, but you buy and
sell it the same way you buy and sell a plot of
land. So there clearly it is considered to be like קרקע karka
or there what we care about is מחובר לקרקע mechubar lekarka and
as long as it's not מטלטלין, metaltelin, it's not true chattel, it
follows the laws of land. Okay. So now we are, so that
is the question about how do you define תלוש ולבסוף חברו. talush
ule'vasof chibro. Now we're going to go back to some of the
שחיטה shechitah laws. So let's take a look.
Where are we? Okay. אמר מר, Amar mar, so we taught: נתן
סכין בכותל ושחט בה שחיטתו כשרה. natan sakin bekotel veshachat bah shechitatu
kesherah. You have your knife in the wall and you use it
to shecht, it's kosher. Remember רש"י Rashi says it means that you
move the animal back and forth over the knife. So אמר רב
ענן אמר שמואל, amar Rav Anan amar Shmuel, לא שנו אלא שסכין
למעלה וצואר בהמה למטה. lo shanu ela shesakin lemalah vetzavar behemah lematah.
That's only true if the animal's neck is underneath the knife and
the knife is pointing down. The knife always has to go to
this part of the neck, it can never go from the back
because then it breaks the then it breaks the spine and makes
the animal a טריפה treifah first. But there's still a question whether
the animal's standing up and the knife is coming from underneath or
the animal's lying down and the knife is coming from above. So
he says in this case where it's attached to the wall, then
the animal has to be has to be below and the knife
above. Why? אבל סכין למטה וצואר בהמה למעלה, aval sakin lematah vetzavar
behemah lemalah, if the animal is standing and the animal is above
and the knife is below and it's pointing up and you're moving
the throat of the animal back and forth over this knife, that's
not going to be good. חיישינן שמא ידרוס. chaishinan shema yidros. We're
afraid you put pressure on the top of the animal and cause
it to cut not through the sharpness but through the pressure. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והקתני, vehatani, we taught
in the
ברייתא: braita: בין שסכין למטה וצואר בהמה למעלה בין שסכין למעלה וצואר
בהמה למטה. bein shesakin lematah vetzavar behemah lemalah bein shesakin lemalah vetzavar
behemah lematah. We taught in the ברייתא braita that whether the knife
is below and the animal's throat is on top of it or
whether the knife is above and the animal's throat is beneath it,
it doesn't matter, it's either way it's valid. So אמר רב זביד,
amar Rav Zevid, לצדדין קתני. letzdadin katani. No, that ברייתא, braita, the
two halves were not talking to one another. What does that mean?
We said like this. We said it could be either the knife
could be either attached or detached. And then we said another statement
which was בין שסכין למטה וצואר בהמה למעלה, bein shesakin lematah vetzavar
behemah lemalah, if the knife is below and the animal is above,
the neck is above, בתלוש. betalush. That will work, but not in
all cases. That'll work if the knife is free, not attached. שסכין
למעלה וצואר בהמה למטה, shesakin lemalah vetzavar behemah lematah, then we said
also of course the knife could be above and the neck of
the throat of the animal below, so that works in all cases,
even במחובר, bemechubar, even attached. So it's true, the knife could be
above or below as long as it's detached. But if the knife
is attached to the wall, then it's only if the animal's throat
is below. Why? Because obviously if you are moving the animal and
not moving the knife, which you have to do when the knife
is attached to the wall, there's a much greater concern that you
are going to put pressure on the throat of the animal and
cause it to be דריסה, derisah, pressure during the act of שחיטה.
shechitah. So if you're moving the knife, we assume that you know
you can move it with one motion, you do it like that,
and even if the animal is above, the natural weight of gravity
of the animal is not enough to create a pressure problem. But
if you're actually moving the animal across the knife and the animal
is standing, then you're afraid that you are going to be pushing
down on the animal at the same time and that will create
a דריסה Drisah problem. Okay, so there you go and again implicit
in this גמרא Gemara is what רש״י Rashi said before, that you
could be moving the animal and not moving the knife. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר
רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa has a better answer how you can
even שחט shacht with the throat above even if it's attached to
the
to the wall, באופא דקליל. Be'ofa dekallil. You're talking about birds, not
about cows. So if you're talking about a bird, there's no problem
about pressure, you know you hold the bird in one hand, you
move it, it's the same type of smooth movement as you do
with the knife itself. So even if you're moving the bird and
not the knife and the bird is above, we're not afraid of
pressure. Okay, so that's a special case, but at least it is
a case in which it wouldn't matter which is on top, which
is on bottom. אמר רב חסדא אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Chisda
amar Rav Yitzchak, רב חסדא Rav Chisda now says in the name
of רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא, Ve'amrei lah bematnita
tana, and some say we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, חמישה דברים
נאמרו בקרומי של קנה. Chamisha devarim ne'emru bekrumei shel kaneh. There are
five restrict, five laws relating to the non-using of a of a
reed. אין שוחטין בה, Ein shochtin bah, you can't use it for
שחיטה. Shechita. Now why not? אמר amar משום mishum said you can
use it for שחיטה. Shechita. So we'll try to reconcile that in
a minute. But the basic concern of this ברייתא Braita or this
statement is that a reed will have there'll be splinters will come
off if you try to use it. So if you try to
use a reed for שחיטה, Shechita, splinters will come off and will
cause a tearing in the animal and will invalidate the שחיטה. Shechita.
So you can't use it for שחיטה Shechita because of splinters. ואין
מלין בה, Ve'ein malin bah, you can't use it for ברית מילה
Bris Milah for obvious similar reasons, even more drastic consequences if splinters
come off. ואין מחתכין בה בשר, Ve'ein mitchatkin bah basar, you don't
use it to cut meat because then some splinters will get left
in the meat and then you'll cut yourself as you're eating the
meat. ואין מחתכין בה שיניים, Ve'ein mechatekin bah shinayim, you don't use
it to pick your teeth, similar reason, splinters will come off and
you'll cut your gums. ואין מקנחין בה, Ve'ein mekanchin bah, and you
do not use it to dry your hands because you will get
splinters in your skin. Okay, so just a lot of good advice
about not using these reeds which causes splinters. Now the גמרא Gemara
looks at it. אין שוחטין בה, Ein shochtin bah, you don't use
it for שחיטה. Shechita. והתניא, Vehatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא,
Braita, בכל שוחטין בין בצור בין בזכוכית בין בקרומי של קנה? Bekol
shochtin bein betzur bein bizchuchit bein bekrumei shel kaneh? You can שחט
shacht with anything, whether it's a rock, whether it's glass, or whether
it's even a reed.
So you can שחט shacht with anything. So how can you say
you can't use it? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר Amar רב
פפא Rav Pappa בסימונא דאגמא. Besimona de'agma. No, what we're talking about,
that type of thing that you can use for שחיטה, Shechita, is
a very certain type of a grass or a reed that grows
in swamps that is very hard and stiff and does not have
splinters. So we're talking about certain types of reeds that don't have
splinters, but the reeds that do have splinters, those you obviously should
not use for שחיטה. Shechita. Okay, now we and so we obviously
don't have to analyze the ברית מילה, Bris Milah, that's obvious. Now
we're going to look at the idea of cutting meat. ואין מחתכין
בה בשר, Ve'ein mitchatkin bah basar, you don't use it to cut
meat. So now we're going to say ah not everybody followed that.
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, the same רב פפא Rav Pappa here that
noticed distinguished between which type of reed, so רב פפא Rav Pappa
understood that this was very contextual, it all depended on the circumstance.
So רב פפא מחתך בה כרבי דגי. Rav Pappa mitchatech bah karbei
dagi. He would use it to cut the innards of fish, he
would use it presumably to clean out fish. Why? דזיגי, Dezigi, because
fish are somewhat transparent and light-skinned and therefore he assumed that any
splinter would come off you would see it in the meat and
you would know to remove it. So רב פפא Rav Pappa was
again said it depends on the context, sometimes it either won't be
a splinter or you'll be able to see the splinters and we're
not concerned. רבה בר רב הונא מחתך בה עופא. Rabbah bar Rav
Huna mitchatech bah ofa. רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna
used it to cut birds, to cut like chicken. דרכיך, Derachich, because
chicken is soft, so he wasn't concerned. Chicken obviously it could be
hidden in the chicken, not like fish, but he said nevertheless he
wasn't concerned there. It's not it's easy to cut, it's soft, and
therefore we're not concerned that the act of cutting will cause some
splinters to splinter off. Last part of this, ואין מקנחין בה, Ve'ein
mekanchin bah, you do not use it to wipe yourself with. So
תפוק ליה, Tipok leh, the גמרא Gemara says why don't we learn
that principle out, it has nothing to do with its splinters. משום
דאמר מר, Mishum de'amar mar, we've taught, המקנח בדבר שהאור שולטת בו
שיניו נושרות. Hamekanayach bedavar sheha'or sholetet bo shinav noshrot. If somebody cleans
himself with something that can be is can be that fire has
dominion over, is flammable, his teeth fall out. Now here we do
not mean literally teeth, and also should clarify what מקנח mekanayach means
because here because מקנח mekanayach here means that if somebody wipes his
orifice, what are you using for your toilet paper? And there was
a concern about witchcraft, in particular the ability to witchcraft. to take
hold on things that were used
to affect you if based on the types of toilet paper you
used. So that somehow it would take some, so somehow whatever witchcraft
was being done against you, it could find a place to settle
on the stuff you're using to wipe yourself with. And that's the
meaning of the idea of שיניו נושרות, shinav noshrot, your teeth fall
out, which it really
means the the skin around the anus would actually would
start to would start falling off, and so obviously would be some
type of serious disease in that location. So anyway you see that
that's the reason you can't use it because fire has dominion over
it. So אמר פפא לקינוח דמכה קאמרנא. Amar Pappa l'kinuach d'maka ka'amrina.
No,
we're not talking about wiping yourself for the bathroom toilet paper, that
cannot be anything that is flammable. But when we're saying that there's
a concern here, we're talking about wiping yourself in other ways, cleaning
your hands or wiping the wiping some type of a wound. There
we're not concerned about the witchcraft issue; there we are concerned though
about the splinters. Okay and with that we end let me just
check one minute. Okay.
All right fine. So now we are done with that little digression
about what do you call it about reeds but we did have
the very important principle both in terms of how do you consider
something attached and תלוש ולבסוף חיברו talush v'levasof chibro I tried to
determine between what the הלכה halacha is looking for defining something as
ground or as מטלטלין metaltelin and this represents a middle category called
מחובר לקרקע mchubar l'karka and we had also the very important discussion
about what do you call it about כח גברא. koach gavra. Okay
now we go to the end of the משנה Mishnah which had
this very summary phrase הכל שוחטין ולעולם שוחטין. Hakol shochtin u'l'olam shochtin.
You can שחט shacht all can שחט shacht and you can always
שחט. shacht. As I said the other day this seems to be
a summary of earlier משניות. Mishnayot. הכל שוחטין Hakol shochtin was the
first משנה Mishnah discussed חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan discussed a
non-Jew. ולעולם שוחטין U'l'olam shochtin was the next two משניות Mishnayot discussing
nighttime, discussing שבת Shabbos and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, obviously you're not
allowed to but the שחיטה shchitah was valid. I even suggested that
this is not a summary line but this actually might have been
the earliest teaching of the משנה. Mishnah. An early משנה Mishnah might
have just said הכל שוחטין ולעולם שוחטין Hakol shochtin u'l'olam shochtin and
then our משניות Mishnayot our first few משניות Mishnayot were elaborations of
what הכל שוחטין Hakol shochtin means and what לעולם שוחטין l'olam shochtin
means. Nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is going to understand that this is
saying something different than we've been saying until now. So let's take
a look. הכל שוחטין Hakol shochtin you can שחט shacht it all
can שחט. shacht. So what does that mean different than what we've
been saying until now? הכל בשחיטה Hakol b'shchitah all things require שחיטה.
shchitah. What does that mean? ואפילו עוף V'afilu of even birds. Because
we know that fish do not require שחיטה. shchitah. Birds require actually
less שחיטה shchitah than animals in the sense you only have to
cut either the trachea or the esophagus, not both. And there even
is an opinion that birds do not require שחיטה shchitah from the
תורה, Torah, only large animals. So here we're reading it to say
even birds biblically require שחיטה. shchitah. ולעולם שוחטין U'l'olam shochtin you have
to שחט shacht at all times so you may or you have
to. Now we're reading it as have to, the same way we
read the birds as you have to שחט shacht birds. So you
have to שחט shacht at all times. What does this mean? מאן
תנא Man tanna who is the תנא? tanna? So אמר רבא רבי
ישמעאל היא. Amar Rava Rabbi Yishmael hee. It's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
דתניא D'tanya we taught in a ברייתא braita כי ירחיב השם אלקיך
את גבולך כאשר דבר לך ואמרת אכלה בשר כי תאוה נפשך לאכל
בשר בכל אות נפשך תאכל בשר. Ki yarchiv Hashem Elokecha et gevulcha
ka'asher diber lach v'amarta ochla vasar ki ta'aveh nafshecha l'echol basar b'chol
avat nafshecha tochal basar. It writes in the תורה Torah in דברים
Devarim God will expand your boundaries you'll come into ישראל Yisrael you're
not going to be living right around the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Now in the desert you all if you want to eat meat
you bring a קרבן korban your שלמים shelamim you eat the meat.
You'll get into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you won't live next to
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you want to slaughter and eat
meat because you have a תאוה ta'avah to eat meat with all
the desire of your heart you may eat meat. So here the
תורה Torah is allowing you to eat meat not bringing it as
a קרבן korban and this is described in Rabbinic terminology as בשר
תאוה basar ta'avah the meat of desire, not the meat of sacrifices,
which the תורה Torah is describing in these verses. So רבי ישמעאל
אומר Rabbi Yishmael omer so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says לא בא
הכתוב אלא להתיר להם בשר תאוה lo ba hakatuv ela l'hatir lahem
basar ta'avah the תורה Torah is only coming to allow meat of
desire שבתחילה נאסר להם בשר תאוה shebat'chila ne'esar lahem basar ta'avah that
the meat of desire was originally forbidden to them in the desert
if they wanted to eat meat they'd bring a קרבן. korban. משנכנסו
לארץ הותר להם בשר תאוה Mishenichnesu l'aretz hutar lahem basar ta'avah when
they came into the land then the meat of desire became permitted
to them. Okay that's the end of רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael statement
it's not clear but רש"י Rashi says this that's the end quote.
So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that's what the verse is saying
you don't have to bring it if you want meat you don't
have to bring it as a קרבן korban you can actually eat
it just wherever you want once you come into ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So now says the גמרא Gemara I might
have thought or says רבא Rava רבא Rava says the following ועכשיו
שגלו v'achshav shegalu now that they've been exiled says רבא Rava working
off of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael יכול יחזור. yachol yachzor. לאיסורן, l'issuran,
maybe they go back to the original state of being forbidden, לאיסורן
הראשון, l'issuran harishon, the original state of being forbidden to eat meat,
right? They were forbidden to eat meat in the wilderness, so now
that they're in exile maybe they should also be forbidden to eat
meat? לעולם שוחטים, L'olam shochtim, therefore our משנה Mishnah says, you always
שחט. shecht. That's to mean you always may שחט, shecht, but you
always must שחט. shecht. So the same way all things, even birds,
require שחיטה, shechitah, at all times we require שחיטה, shechitah, even when
we're no longer in Israel, you require שחיטה, shechitah, well actually not
so much require, but what it's saying here is that you're able,
you're actually—I misspoke—it's not so much require, but you're able to שחט
shecht at all times. So even though you're no longer in Israel
with a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the permission of meat still exists.
You're even able to שחט shecht and eat meat nowadays. Quite an
interesting implicit theology here that the only permission to eat meat was
when there was a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So maybe the bringing
of קרבנות korbanot in some way validated the fact that you were
eating meat in general. But when you don't have that and when
you're in exile, or maybe when you're not in an ideal state,
you don't merit eating meat or it doesn't validate the eating of
meat. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara does not buy into this because
if anything it says the—the more natural theology is the opposite. So
מתקיף לה רב יוסף, Matkif lah Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
asks on this argument, היי לעולם שוחטים, hai l'olam shochtim, first of
all, it should not say you always שחט, shecht, because the real
point is you're always allowed to eat meat. So it should have
said לעולם שוחטים ואוכלים מיבעי ליה, l'olam shochtim v'ochlim mibei lei, it
should have said you always can שחט shecht and eat meat because
the חידוש chiddush is not that you שחט, shecht, the חידוש chiddush
is that you're allowed to eat meat. That's number one. ועוד, Ve'od,
and number two, מעיקרא מאי טעמא איתסר, me'ikara mai ta'ama itassar, why
was it meat originally forbidden in the desert? משום דהוו מקרבי למשכן,
mishum d'havu mikravi l'mishkan, because they were so close to the—to the
משכן mishkan that don't just eat meat סתם, stam, bring it as
a קרבן korban if you're able to, you're so close. ולבסוף מאי
טעמא אישתרי, U'l'vsof mai ta'ama ishtari, why were they allowed to eat
meat without bringing it as a קרבן korban in the land of
Israel? דהוו מירחקי ממשכן, d'havu mirchaki m'mishkan, because they were very distant
from the Temple. So the permission to eat meat is because of
the impossibility or—not the impossibility, the difficulty in bringing a קרבן. korban.
If that's why you're permitted to eat meat, then he says וכל
שכן, v'kol sheken, certainly, השתא, hashta, nowadays that there's no Temple and
we're in exile, דאיחרקו טפי, d'itcharku tefei, they're even more distant from
a Temple. There's no Temple and we're in exile. So therefore, why
is it a חידוש chiddush to say that we're allowed to eat
meat in exile? If anything, of course we're allowed to eat meat
in exile. There's no possibility of bringing a קרבן. korban. So the
משנה Mishnah cannot mean to tell me that you can always eat
meat even nowadays. It would have used the word אוכלים ochlim and
that's taken for granted that we're obviously still allowed to eat meat
nowadays. So why is the משנה Mishnah telling me לעולם שוחטים? l'olam
shochtim? That we will talk about as we continue tomorrow. Okay, take
care everybody, have a good day. We'll end here.